Finding Aid for the Getty Education Institute for the Arts, Event and Publication Images, 1985-1997 IA20018
Institutional Records and Archives
Event and publication images
1985-1997
Institutional Records and Archives
Getty Education Institute for the Arts
IA20018
7.26 Linear Feet (16 boxes)
Records consist of black-and-white and color photographs, color slides, black-and-white and color negatives, forms, and letters, 1985-1997, created for and used by the Getty Education Institute (GEI), and housed in the Slide Library. The images depict conferences and seminars organized and hosted by the GEI; art appreciation instruction in elementary school classrooms; adults attending lectures and museums; and publication artwork.
Acquisition Information
The records described in this finding aid originated in accession no. 1999.IA.05.
Technical Requirements
Slides require slide-viewing equipment; audiocassettes require audio equipment.
Restrictions on Access
The records described in accession 1999.IA.05 are available for use by qualified researchers.
The following types of records are permanently closed: records containing personal information, records that compromise security or operations, legal communications, legal work product, and records related to donors. The J. Paul Getty Trust reserves the right to restrict access to any records held by the Institutional Archives.
Scope and Content
Records consist of black-and-white and color photographs, color slides, black-and-white and color negatives, forms, and letters, 1985-1997, created for and used by the Getty Education Institute, and originally housed in the Slide Library. The images depict conferences and seminars organized and/or hosted by the GEI, such as "Education in Art Future Building" and "Beyond the Three R's"; art appreciation instruction in elementary school classrooms; adults attending lectures and museums; and publication covers. Also included are photographs of GEI Director Lani Duke's farewell reception. The images are primarily documentary in nature, providing a photographic record of many of the GEI's activities. It is not clear whether or not the Slide Library was responsible for the creation of the images.
Some images were used in specific publications of the GEI, such as Celebrating pluralism: art, education, and cultural diversity by F. Graeme Chalmers (c.1996).
Arrangement
These records are first arranged by subject and then alphabetically within each subject. The subjects are: Children and art appreciation education; Conferences, congresses, seminars, meetings; Adults in lectures and museums; Publication information; and Miscellaneous. These subjects are drawn from the contents of the images themselves, and the titles of the original binders. Numbers in parentheses indicate the original binder number (not all binders were numbered).
Administrative History
The Getty Center for Education in the Arts, also known as the Getty Education Institute for the Arts (GEI), was founded in 1982 with the mission of improving the quality and status of arts education in the nation's public schools. The GEI's programs were guided by three premises: the visual arts should be an essential part of every child's education because knowledge of the arts is a principal means of understanding human experiences and transmitting cultural values; art education's content must be broadened to include instruction in art production, art history, art criticism, and aesthetics—an approach known as discipline-based art education (DBAE); and the most effective art education programs are based on partnerships among teachers, administrators, artists, museums, universities, and parents.
During its first 10 years, the GEI concentrated on the implementation and dissemination of DBAE. This was achieved by advocacy of the value of arts in education, through the dissemination of print publications and videotapes, national conferences, and collaborative projects; professional development for school and university personnel, through inservice programs such as the Los Angeles Institute; theory development to encourage evolution of DBAE, through seminars, doctoral fellowships, and the commissioning of scholarly publications; curriculum development to support creation of model instructional materials; and special initiatives to encourage others to champion DBAE.
In addition to improving the quality of arts education in primary and secondary schools, the GEI also concentrated on the education of museum visitors. Focus group research and other studies resulted in a number of publications aimed at the museum world.
The GEI was dissolved in 1999; some aspects of its activities may have been absorbed by other programs.
Art -- Study and teaching; Black-and-white negatives; Black-and-white prints (photographs); Forms (documents); Congresses and conventions; Letters (correspondence); Color negatives; Color slides; Color photographs; Audiocassettes; Art teachers -- Training of; Getty Center for Education in the Arts; Getty Education Institute for the Arts. Slide Library; J. Paul Getty Trust; Duke, Lani (Leilani Lattin)
- Children and art appreciation education
  - Adults observing in the classroom (#4):
    - ABC Unified School District, July 1985 (Box 1999.IA.05-1, Folder 1)
    - Bellflower Unified School District, July 17, 1985 (Box 1999.IA.05-1, Folder 2)
    - El Segundo Unified School District, June 1986 (Box 1999.IA.05-1, Folder 3)
    - Lynwood Unified School District, Summer 1983 (Box 1999.IA.05-1, Folder 4)
    - Montebello Unified School District, July 1985 (Box 1999.IA.05-1, Folder 5)
    - Torrance Unified School District, June 1986 (Box 1999.IA.05-1, Folder 6)
    - Unidentified schools, circa 1986 (Box 1999.IA.05-1, Folder 7)
  - Artwork on display (#3):
    - Bellflower Unified School District, July 17, 1985 (Box 1999.IA.05-1, Folder 8)
    - Charter Oaks Unified School District, March 8, 1985 (Box 1999.IA.05-1, Folder 9)
    - Compton Unified School District, June 6, 1986 (Box 1999.IA.05-1, Folder 10)
    - Culver City Unified School District, February 1987 (Box 1999.IA.05-1, Folder 11)
    - Downey Unified School District, February 1987 (Box 1999.IA.05-1, Folder 12)
    - Eastside Unified School District, June 3, 1986 (Box 1999.IA.05-1, Folder 13)
    - El Segundo Unified School District, June 1986 (Box 1999.IA.05-1, Folder 14)
    - Garvey School District, April 29, 1988 (Box 1999.IA.05-1, Folder 15)
    - LA Unified School District Region A, April 1987 (Box 1999.IA.05-1, Folder 16)
    - LA Unified School District Region C, circa 1987 (Box 1999.IA.05-1, Folder 17)
    - LA Unified School District Region E (Emelita), February 1988 (Box 1999.IA.05-1, Folder 18)
    - LA Unified School District Region E (Sherman Oaks), circa 1988 (Box 1999.IA.05-1, Folder 19)
    - Santa Monica-Malibu Unified School District, circa 1988 (Box 1999.IA.05-1, Folder 20)
    - Montebello Unified School District, circa 1988 (Box 1999.IA.05-1, Folder 21)
    - Newhall Unified School District, circa 1988 (Box 1999.IA.05-1, Folder 22)
    - Norwalk-LaMirada Unified School District, circa 1988 (Box 1999.IA.05-1, Folder 23)
    - Torrance Unified School District, Art Fair, circa 1988 (Box 1999.IA.05-1, Folder 24)
    - Torrance Unified School District, February 1987 (Box 1999.IA.05-1, Folder 25)
    - Torrance Unified School District, circa 1988 (Box 1999.IA.05-1, Folder 26)
    - Unidentified schools, circa 1988 (Box 1999.IA.05-1, Folder 27)
  - Book 33 classroom photography:
    - 1996, [1-2 of 4] (Box 1999.IA.05-1, Folder 28-29)
    - 1996, [3-4 of 4] (Box 1999.IA.05-2, Folder 1-2)
  - Children in museums (#5), 1986; [2 files] (Box 1999.IA.05-2, Folder 3)
  - Children making, looking at and reading about art (#2):
    - Bellflower Unified School District, July 17, 1985 (Box 1999.IA.05-2, Folder 5)
    - Charter Oaks Unified School District, March 8, 1985 (Box 1999.IA.05-2, Folder 6)
    - Compton Unified School District, June 6, 1986 (Box 1999.IA.05-2, Folder 7)
    - Culver City Unified School District, February 1987 (Box 1999.IA.05-2, Folder 8)
    - Downey Unified School District, February 1987 (Box 1999.IA.05-2, Folder 9)
    - Eastside Union School District, June 3, 1986 (Box 1999.IA.05-2, Folder 10)
    - Los Angeles Institute, 1983 (Box 1999.IA.05-2, Folder 11)
    - LA Unified School District, Region A, April 1987 (Box 1999.IA.05-2, Folder 12)
    - LA Unified School District, Region B, June 11, 1986 (Box 1999.IA.05-2, Folder 13)
    - LA Unified School District, Region E, February 1987 (Box 1999.IA.05-2, Folder 14)
    - Montebello Unified School District, Garfield, circa 1987 (Box 1999.IA.05-2, Folder 15)
    - Montebello Unified School District, Washington, circa 1987 (Box 1999.IA.05-2, Folder 16)
    - Sulphur Springs Union School District, June 10, 1986 (Box 1999.IA.05-2, Folder 17)
    - Torrance Unified School District, June 1986 (Box 1999.IA.05-2, Folder 18)
    - Torrance Unified School District, April 1987 (Box 1999.IA.05-2, Folder 19)
    - Torrance Unified School District, February 1987 (Box 1999.IA.05-2, Folder 20)
    - Garfield School, Lindstrom School, Gonsalves School, July 1985 (Box 1999.IA.05-2, Folder 21)
    - Unidentified schools, circa 1987 (Box 1999.IA.05-2, Folder 22)
  - Children's artwork, undated; [1 of 2] (Box 1999.IA.05-2, Folder 23)
  - Children's artwork, undated; [2 of 2] (Box 1999.IA.05-3, Folder 1)
  - Classroom photography for GEI book "Creating and Beyond,", undated (Box 1999.IA.05-3, Folder 2-5)
  - Classroom scenes (#1):
    - Bellflower Unified School District, July 17, 1985 (Box 1999.IA.05-3, Folder 6)
    - Charter Oaks Unified School District, March 8, 1985 (Box 1999.IA.05-3, Folder 7)
    - Compton Unified School District, June 6, 1986 (Box 1999.IA.05-3, Folder 8)
    - Culver City Unified School District, February 1987 (Box 1999.IA.05-3, Folder 9)
    - Downey Unified School District, February 1987 (Box 1999.IA.05-3, Folder 10)
    - Eastside Union School District, June 3, 1986 (Box 1999.IA.05-3, Folder 11)
    - El Segundo Unified School District, June 1986 (Box 1999.IA.05-3, Folder 12)
    - Garvey School District, April 29, 1988 (Box 1999.IA.05-3, Folder 13)
    - LA Unified School District Region B, June 11, 1986 (Box 1999.IA.05-3, Folder 14)
    - Lynwood Unified School District, March 6, 1985 (Box 1999.IA.05-3, Folder 15)
    - Lynwood Unified School District, March 1984 (Box 1999.IA.05-3, Folder 16)
    - Norwalk-La Mirada Unified School District, October 1985 (Box 1999.IA.05-3, Folder 17)
    - Sulphur Springs Union School District, June 10, 1986 (Box 1999.IA.05-4, Folder 1)
    - Torrance Unified School District, June 1986 (Box 1999.IA.05-4, Folder 2)
    - Garfield School, Lindstrom School, Gonsalves School, July 1985 (Box 1999.IA.05-4, Folder 3)
    - Unidentified schools, circa 1985 (Box 1999.IA.05-4, Folder 4)
  - DBAE (Discipline Based Art Education) Implementation (#15):
    - Churchill High School, September 21, 1988 (Box 1999.IA.05-4, Folder 5)
    - Kennedy Junior High School, September 21, 1988 (Box 1999.IA.05-4, Folder 6)
    - Coburg Elementary School, September 22, 1988 (Box 1999.IA.05-4, Folder 7)
    - Howard Elementary School, September 30, 1988 (Box 1999.IA.05-4, Folder 8)
    - Santa Clara Elementary School, September 30, 1988 (Box 1999.IA.05-4, Folder 9)
    - Sheldon High School, October 3, 1988 (Box 1999.IA.05-4, Folder 10)
    - Summer Institute, Parker Elementary School, August 22-25, 1988 (Box 1999.IA.05-4, Folder 11)
    - Summer Institute, Parker Elementary School, black and white photos, August 22-25, 1988 (Box 1999.IA.05-4, Folder 12)
  - Discipline Based Art Education (DBAE) implementation, Eugene school district, participant and photograph information, 1989; [3 files] (Box 1999.IA.05-4, Folder 13-15)
  - Discipline Based Art Education, Portland public schools:
    - 1990, [1-3 of 4 files] (Box 1999.IA.05-4, Folder 16-18)
    - 1990, [4 of 4 files] (Box 1999.IA.05-5, Folder 1)
  - GEI classroom photos, undated (Box 1999.IA.05-5, Folder 2)
  - Joseph Germain's classroom, June 1997; [2 files] (Box 1999.IA.05-5, Folder 3-4)
  - Lenox school district, 1997 (Box 1999.IA.05-5, Folder 5)
  - [Miscellaneous images, primarily children in classrooms creating artwork], undated (Box 1999.IA.05-5, Folder 6)
  - Release forms, Carver Elementary, November 1996 (Box 1999.IA.05-5, Folder 7)
  - Release forms, classroom shoot, 1996; [2 files] (Box 1999.IA.05-5, Folder 8-9)
  - Release forms, Encino School, 1995 (Box 1999.IA.05-5, Folder 10)
  - Release forms, Felton Elementary School, 1997 (Box 1999.IA.05-5, Folder 11)
  - Slides and photos from GEI events, undated (Box 1999.IA.05-5, Folder 12)
- Conferences, congresses, seminars, meetings
  - Austin Issues II:
    - undated, [1 of 5 files] (Box 1999.IA.05-5, Folder 13)
    - undated, [2-5 of 5 files] (Box 1999.IA.05-6, Folder 1-4)
  - Austin Issues III, undated (Box 1999.IA.05-6, Folder 2)
  - Beyond the Three R's, volume 1, January 12-14, 1995; [2 files] (Box 1999.IA.05-6, Folder 3-4)
  - Beyond the Three R's, volume 2, January 12-14, 1995; [4 files] (Box 1999.IA.05-6, Folder 5-8)
  - Beyond the Three R's conference negatives, January 12-14, 1995; [2 files] (Box 1999.IA.05-6, Folder 9-10)
  - Contact sheets, Beyond the Three R's national conference leadership forum:
    - circa 1995, [1-2 of 5 files] (Box 1999.IA.05-6, Folder 11-15)
    - circa 1995, [3-5 of 5 files] (Box 1999.IA.05-7, Folder 1-3)
  - Center-sponsored seminars and conferences: Roundtable II, Seattle, December 1985; [6 files] (Box 1999.IA.05-7, Folder 4-8)
    General note
    [Folder 6 moved to Publication information section.]
  - GEI Advisory Committee meeting, October 1996 (Box 1999.IA.05-7, Folder 10)
  - GEI slide presentation tapes, 1985 (Box 1999.IA.05-7, Folder 11)
  - GEI slide-tape presentation, original slides, 1985 (Box 1999.IA.05-8, Folder 1)
  - GEI slide presentation, master set, 1985 (Box 1999.IA.05-8, Folder 2)
  - GEI slide presentation, duplicates, 1985 (Box 1999.IA.05-8, Folder 3)
  - Institute/L.A. related meetings and events (#10):
    - Introduction to new school districts, 1985 (Box 1999.IA.05-8, Folder 4)
    - Norwalk-La Mirada school district DBAE event, February 1, 1985 (Box 1999.IA.05-8, Folder 5)
    - Superintendents advisory panel and school board presidents, February 14, 1985 (Box 1999.IA.05-8, Folder 6)
    - Bellflower Unified School District certificate award ceremony, March 21, 1985 (Box 1999.IA.05-8, Folder 7)
    - Laguna retreat, April 27, 1985 (Box 1999.IA.05-8, Folder 8)
    - New school faculty meeting, May 2, 1985 (Box 1999.IA.05-8, Folder 9)
    - Getty Institute/LA faculty and advisory committee meeting, February 22, 1985 (Box 1999.IA.05-8, Folder 10)
    - Faculty advisors meeting, May 3, 1985 (Box 1999.IA.05-8, Folder 11)
    - Faculty and area coordinators meetings, May 4, 1985 (Box 1999.IA.05-8, Folder 12)
    - Charter participant's reunion, May 16, 1985 (Box 1999.IA.05-8, Folder 13)
    - Evaluation meeting, August 30, 1985 (Box 1999.IA.05-8, Folder 14)
  - Kids Congress, conference on art, 1997; [2 files] (Box 1999.IA.05-16, Folder 4-5)
  - Leadership conference negatives, circa 1997; [2 files] (Box 1999.IA.05-8, Folder 15-16)
  - Leadership conference, January 1997 (Box 1999.IA.05-8, Folder 17)
  - Miscellaneous summer institutes, undated; [2 files] (Box 1999.IA.05-9, Folder 1-2)
  - More Teacher Institutes (#36), 1996-1997 (Box 1999.IA.05-9, Folder 3)
  - Nebraska Regional Institute (#12), circa 1988; [4 files] (Box 1999.IA.05-9, Folder 4-7)
  - Photographs, negatives, slides from multiple events, undated; [5 files] (Box 1999.IA.05-9, Folder 8-12)
  - 2nd National Conference "Education in Art Future Building" photographs, undated; [4 files] (Box 1999.IA.05-10, Folder 2-5)
  - 2nd National Conference "Education in Art Future Building" negatives and contact sheets, undated; [3 files] (Box 1999.IA.05-10, Folder 6-8)
  - Second National Conference (#18), undated; [2 files] (Box 1999.IA.05-10, Folder 9-10)
  - Snowbird meetings, 1987 (Box 1999.IA.05-10, Folder 11)
  - Unidentified conferences, undated (Box 1999.IA.05-10, Folder 12)
  - Unidentified event, undated (Box 1999.IA.05-11, Folder 1)
  - Unidentified event[s], undated (Box 1999.IA.05-16, Folder 7)
    [14 contact sheets possibly depicting Beyond the Three R's conference.]
  - Unidentified event negatives, undated (Box 1999.IA.05-11, Folder 2)
  - Unidentified slide presentation, undated (Box 1999.IA.05-11, Folder 3)
  - Wave Your Banner Project (Kid's Congress on Art), 1996; [2 files] (Box 1999.IA.05-11, Folder 4-5)
- Adults in lectures and museums
  - Adults in Museums (#6):
    - Getty Museum, 1985 (Box 1999.IA.05-11, Folder 6)
    - Getty and Los Angeles County Museum of Art, Museum of Contemporary Art, circa 1985 (Box 1999.IA.05-11, Folder 7)
    - Getty reception and tour, Newhall School District, April 12, 1985 (Box 1999.IA.05-11, Folder 8)
    - Huntington Museum, 1985; [4 of 9] (Box 1999.IA.05-11, Folder 9)
    - Los Angeles County Museum of Art, 1985 (Box 1999.IA.05-11, Folder 10)
    - Museum of Contemporary Art, 1985 (Box 1999.IA.05-11, Folder 11)
    - Norton Simon, 1985 (Box 1999.IA.05-11, Folder 12)
    - Pacific Asia Museum, 1985 (Box 1999.IA.05-11, Folder 13)
    - University of California Los Angeles, 1985 (Box 1999.IA.05-11, Folder 14)
  - Adults in lectures (#7): Getty Institute, LA, 1983; 1984 (Box 1999.IA.05-11, Folder 15)
  - Adults in lectures (#8):
    - Observations by Institute faculty, June 19, 1985 (Box 1999.IA.05-12, Folder 1)
    - Panel discussions, Moving from Theory to Action, circa 1985 (Box 1999.IA.05-12, Folder 2)
    - Getty Institute, 1985; [5 files] (Box 1999.IA.05-12, Folder 3-7)
  - Adults in lectures (#9): Getty Institute, LA, 1987; [3 files] (Box 1999.IA.05-12, Folder 8-10)
  - Ohio Regional Institute: Adults in lectures and workshops, undated; [1 of 2] (Box 1999.IA.05-12, Folder 11)
  - Ohio Regional Institute: Adults in museums, undated; [2 of 2] (Box 1999.IA.05-13, Folder 1)
- Publication information
  - Art News picture of Lani Duke, August 1988; [6 of 6] (Box 1999.IA.05-7, Folder 9)
    [Originally housed in binder entitled "Center-sponsored seminars and conferences." See "Conferences, congresses, seminars, meetings" for remainder of the material in this binder.]
  - F. Graeme Chalmers, "Art, Education and Cultural Diversity" images and permissions, 1993 (Box 1999.IA.05-13, Folder 2)
  - Getty photos, publications information, undated (Box 1999.IA.05-13, Folder 3)
  - Publication covers, undated; [4 files] (Box 1999.IA.05-13, Folder 4-7)
  - Unidentified photographs and slides (for book), undated (Box 1999.IA.05-13, Folder 8)
  - [Unidentified photos, possibly used for publication], undated (Box 1999.IA.05-16, Folder 6)
    [5 photographs on backings.]
  - [Unidentified photos, possibly used for publication], undated (Box 1999.IA.05-16, Folder 8)
    [7 large color photographs, and negatives.]
- Miscellaneous
  - Artwork from other sources, undated (Box 1999.IA.05-13, Folder 9)
  - Assorted "best of" slides, undated; [1 of 2] (Box 1999.IA.05-13, Folder 10)
  - Assorted "best of" slides, undated; [2 of 2] (Box 1999.IA.05-14, Folder 1)
  - GEI Exhibition booth, undated; [1 of 2] (Box 1999.IA.05-14, Folder 2-3)
  - GEI staff, scholars, interns, undated; [5 files] (Box 1999.IA.05-14, Folder 4-8)
  - Images on loan, 1996-1998 (Box 1999.IA.05-14, Folder 9)
  - Image return forms, undated (Box 1999.IA.05-14, Folder 10)
  - Lani Duke farewell reception, June 29, 1998; [1 of 2] (Box 1999.IA.05-14, Folder 11)
  - Lani Duke farewell reception, June 29, 1998; [2 of 2] (Box 1999.IA.05-15, Folder 1)
  - Memo from R. Harsh re: photography, April 26, 1995 (Box 1999.IA.05-15, Folder 2)
  - Memos, forms re: policies and procedures, 1988-1989; [1 of 2] (Box 1999.IA.05-15, Folder 3)
  - Memos, forms re: policies and procedures, 1988-1989; [2 of 2] (Box 1999.IA.05-15, Folder 4)
  - Memo re: Regional Institute Grant Program photo documentation project, 1998 (Box 1999.IA.05-15, Folder 5)
  - Miscellaneous (#14):
    - Title House slides, undated (Box 1999.IA.05-15, Folder 6)
    - Demonstin Residence, April 15, 1985 (Box 1999.IA.05-15, Folder 7)
    - Works [of] art from the J. Paul Getty Museum, undated (Box 1999.IA.05-15, Folder 8)
    - Individual works from Huntington Museum, undated (Box 1999.IA.05-15, Folder 9)
    - Murals in Santa Monica and works from the Norton Simon Museum, undated (Box 1999.IA.05-15, Folder 10)
    - Works from the Pacific Asia Museum, undated (Box 1999.IA.05-15, Folder 11)
    - Works from Museum of Cultural History, UCLA, undated (Box 1999.IA.05-15, Folder 12)
    - Cartoon slides for Center "roasts", undated (Box 1999.IA.05-15, Folder 13)
  - [Miscellaneous images], undated; [2 files] (Box 1999.IA.05-15, Folder 14-15)
  - Release forms, 1994 (Box 1999.IA.05-15, Folder 16)
  - Release forms, 1996 (Box 1999.IA.05-15, Folder 17)
  - Release forms, November 1996 (Box 1999.IA.05-15, Folder 18)
  - Release forms, 1997 (Box 1999.IA.05-15, Folder 19)
  - Slide labels, undated (Box 1999.IA.05-15, Folder 20)
  - Unidentified event, undated (Box 1999.IA.05-15, Folder 21)
  - Video stills (#28), undated (Box 1999.IA.05-15, Folder 22)